# MattRalston interdisciplinary life scientist

#### contact

15 Innovation Way Newark, DE 19717

302.547.2437

mrals@udel.edu matthewralston.github.io LinkedIn:matthewralston

#### wet-lab

RNA-seq, RT-PCR Northern & Western Spectrometry, HPLC Immunofluorescence Mammalian cell culture Anaerobic fermentation

#### dry-lab

♥ Ruby/Rails, R Bash, Python, Julia Matlab, LATEX, Racket MvSQL. SQLite Javascript, CSS/HTML

#### **summary**

A versatile researcher with solid biochemical training and experience producing and interpreting large 'omic datasets. Deeply enjoys research and development, from experimental design to analysis. Offers interdisciplinary expertise for teams of scientists, engineers, and analysts.

#### education

2012-2015 **Masters** of Bioinformatics and Computational Biology **3.97** 

> Assembling Improved Gene Annotations in Clostridium acetobutylicum with RNA Sequencing.

First strand-specific catalog of transcripts in the genus Clostridia.

**Bachelors** of Biochemistry 2008-2012 University of Delaware

Minor in Biochemical Engineering

## **experience**

2012-Now **DELAWARE BIOTECHNOLOGY INSTITUTE** 

Newark, DE Graduate Research Assistant

Accomplishments:

• Developed and utilized laboratory and computational workflows for deep RNA sequencing.

- Produced a catalog of transcripts from multiple culture conditions.
- Built and launched a genome browser for research community.

2010-2012 **Center for Translational Cancer Research** Newark, DE

Undergraduate Research Fellow

Investigated the BMP-signaling pathway in colon cancer cell lines and fresh colon tissue.

#### awards

2013 Winning Proposal Fraunhoffer CMB

Awarded for a revision to a vaccine production process. Part of IGERT Busi-

ness, Ethics, and Communication course.

2008 **Merit Based Scholarship** University of Delaware

### leadership

2014 **Bioinformatic Student Association** Newark, DE

President

Lead a UNIX and HPC workshop and won funding for student development

workshops.

2013 **IGERT Business, Ethics, and Communication Project** Newark, DE

Project Manager

Won a proposal for a revision to Fraunhoffer CMB's GMP vaccine production

process.

# **publications**

- "The Transcriptome of *C. acetobutylicum*: Deep Sequencing and Assembly," in preparation.
- "The Clostridium small RNome that response to stress: the paradigm and importance of toxic metabolite stress in C. acetobutylicum", contributing author. BMC Genomics. 14.1 (2013): 849.
- "Overexpression of the *L. plantarum* peptidoglycan biosynthesis murA2 gene increases the tolerance of *E. coli* to alcohols and enhances ethanol production", contributing author. *Applied Microbiology and Biotechnology* 98.19 (2014): 8399-8411.